<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text"></title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-07-01T00:32:54+02:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Got</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Data analysis in Awk]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/articles/data-analysis-in-awk/" />
  <id>/articles/data-analysis-in-awk</id>
  <published>2016-06-18T20:37:17+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-18T20:37:17+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I recently encountered a problem that required writing a script to parse and analyze log data and output aggregated statistics.
The parsing goals included opening a file containing syslog data, finding all lines containing a specific pattern and extracting values corresponding to specific entries from the lines. The result of the analysis was supposed to be the totals for each of the values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My gut reaction was that this is the kind of problem in which Awk excels: finding patterns in text and analyzing file contents. While working out the solution, I came to reflect on the powerful features of Awk such as associative arrays: a data structure that I had previously used many times without giving much thought. Associative arrays in Awk are like normal arrays, except that they can be indexed with strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For illustration purposes, assume we have a syslog file with lines that look like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
application=http original=632 terminal=1607
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to add all the “original” and “terminal” values corresponding to each application. Awk arrays allow us to neatly express this as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
original[$1] += $2
terminal[$1] += $3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does the proper initialization when &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt; is not present in the &lt;code&gt;original&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt; arrays. Accessing array elements is achieved through a simple loop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
for (val in array)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete solution is in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Tiglas/syslog-analysis&quot;&gt;this Github repository&lt;/a&gt;. For comparison, I implemented the solution in Python as well.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/data-analysis-in-awk/&quot;&gt;Data analysis in Awk&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on June 18, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Floating Point Arithmetic ]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/articles/floating-point-arithmetic/" />
  <id>/articles/floating-point-arithmetic</id>
  <published>2016-04-17T19:17:56+02:00</published>
  <updated>2016-04-17T19:17:56+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;My first time digging around floating piont arithmetic invariably led me to the paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19957-01/806-3568/ncg_goldberg.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What Every Computer Scientist Should Know About Floating-Point Arithmetic&lt;/em&gt;, by David Goldberg&lt;/a&gt;. I found the paper a great read, but I’ll admit I had to go through several re-reads and references from other sources to finally grasp its contents. In this post, I give a much more gentle treatment of floating point arithmetic, inspired by one of the best books I have had the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0735611319/?tag=rorg-20&quot;&gt;pleasure of reading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A natural place to start off is to look at the subset of numbers called whole numbers (referred to as integers by computer programmers) and rational numbers. Numbers such as 20, 3442 and 9992400 fall into the former category whereas 3/4, 1/3 and 7/30 are in the latter one. Rational numbers are expressed as a ratio of two whole numbers and can be equivalently expressed in fractional form - 3/4 is 0.75 for instance. The representation is depicted below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.75 = 1x10&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; + 7x10&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; + 5x10&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digits to the left of the decimal point are multiplied by positive powers of 10 while those to the right are multiplied by negative powers of 10.
Even so, some rational numbers are not easy to represent, such as 1/3, whose fractional form is 0.3333333333…, a never-ending stream of 3’s. On the other hand, irrational numbers (such as √2) do not a repeating fractional sequence.
The scientific notation is very useful for representing very large and small numbers. Expressed in this notation, the number 490,000,000 = 4.9 x 10&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt; and 0.0000000026 = 2.6 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-10&lt;/sup&gt;. The notation provides a standardized format for numbers - in these examples, 4.9 and 2.6 are the fractional part or significand, the exponent is the power to which 10 is raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers represent numbers in binary form, sequences of 1’s and 0’s. Floating point notation is based on the scientific notation, which we have examined for decimal numbers. So how do we represent fractional numbers in binary? Just like in the decimal number system, a binary point is used, with significand bits to the left of the binary point multiplied by negative powers of 2 and those to the right positive powers of 2. Concretely, 101.1101 is expressed as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1x2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; +
0x2&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; +
1x2&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; +
1x2&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; +
1x2&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt; +
0x2&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; +
1x2&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is 5.8125 in decimal. In binary scientific notation, the number 101.1101 is written as 1.011101x2&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, with the normalized significand greater than or equal to 1 but less than 2. This has the implication that the left of the decimal point in a significand always has a 1 in a normalized binary floating-point number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most computers support &lt;em&gt;IEEE Standard for Binary Floating-Point Arithmetic&lt;/em&gt;, which defines single precision (requiring 4 bytes) and double precision (requiring 8 bytes) formats. The main advantage of floating-point representation over fixed-point representation is the ability to represent numbers of vastly differing magnitudes, from the radius of an atom to the distance from the earth to the sun. The precision of floating-point representation will have a bearing on how numbers are represented and the results of ensuing arithmetic operations. Single precision floating-point numbers have a 24-bit representation. What this means is that numbers differing by less than 1 part in 2&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt; will have the same representation. Represented as single precision floating-point numbers, 16,777,216 and 16,777,217 are identical. This may, or may not be an issue but it is something the programmer ought to be aware of. Adding a very large floating-point number to a very small one or comparing two floating-point numbers may produce surprising results too. As such, one needs to be careful when writing programs that operate on floating-point numbers. One technique for instance involves sorting the numbers to be added and performing the addition in increasing order of size to ensure that small numbers reflect in the final result. Instead of comparing two floating-point numbers for equality, one can instead determine if the difference between them is less than some threshold value and base control logic on this. For instance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
if (float1 == float2)
# Do something
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
epsilon = 1.0*10^-8
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
if (abs(float1 - float2) &amp;lt; epsilon)
# Do something
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further reading&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Every Computer Scientist Should Know About Floating-Point Arithmetic &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19957-01/806-3568/ncg_goldberg.html&quot;&gt;https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E19957-01/806-3568/ncg_goldberg.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/floating-point-arithmetic/&quot;&gt;Floating Point Arithmetic &lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 17, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Find a Pizzeria in Copenhagen]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/how-to-find-a-pizzeria-in-denmark/" />
  <id>/blog/how-to-find-a-pizzeria-in-denmark</id>
  <published>2016-02-28T20:54:43+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-28T20:54:43+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Last week I visited Copenhagen some good friends of mine. It was one of those things that I didn’t really take time to think about, but rather decided to go on the spur of the moment. A perfect way to spend a weekend as it turned out.
My first taste of Danish food was in the form brunch for which we had to brave the elements to get to. As I soon discovered, the food was great and the buffet offered a healthy variety. Having had our fill, we began exploring the city like good old tourists do, with the exception that we were accompanied by our two Danish friends. The city art museum quite stood out for me: the art on display magnificently explored human history and culture. We found time to visit the Little Mermaid and I have to admit it produced little excitement in me, perhaps due to my lack of acquintance with the works of $AUTHOR. As the day wore on, we decided to have dinner at a nearby pizzeria, the subject of this story. And so began an evening of pizza, good conversation and laughter. It was also one of my friend’s birthday too. After dinner, jetlag began our lack of sleep began to show and we were simply too tired to go out (the best laid plans of men and mice). 
The hostel I stayed in wasn’t exactly heavenly, but it was fine. I got a little shock though as one of the guys sharing the room burst in and asked in very colorful language “whoever took his wallet to return, just the wallet, ‘cos he didn’t need the money” as he couldn’t go home as a result. No one answered, except for a few sleepy stares. I set out the following day to find the pizzeria we had been to the previous day. So I took the map only to realize that
I couldn’t remember the name (I usually go straight for the pizza and skip the pizzeria names). I asked the friends who were with me, but none could remember the name despite being vaguely aware of the location within the City. But then I really needed to go back to that pizzeria. So with a map, I set out to retrace our steps from last night. However, I remembered that we took bus 3A and one of our other friends took bus 5A at the same bus stop. And then boom!
it hit me that I could actually trace my way by looking for the location on the map where bus 3A and 5A shared a road segment. I hopped onto bus 350S and asked the burly driver where I should drop off, but his reply was dismissively “I can’t help you young man, use your phone” while laughing. Having listened to my ordeal, an old man in the same bus came and asked where I wanted go. He was old, his steps considered and his vision far from perfect. But he asked me to tell him the name of the street I wanted to go to. $STREETNAME I said. Granted, my Danish isn’t great, but after several repititions he was able to get where I wanted to go. And so he gave me small tour of the city as we rode the bus, pointing out historical artefacts and tourist attractions all the while promising that he will show me where to alight. And show me did, even going further to point at with his fingers while smiling. The gesture was so touching.
It took me a short while to locate the place. And then I explained to the waiter why I was there. And ordered another pizza. Which was good. The city of Copenhagen has a lot more to offer than merely pizza.
The people actually talk in buses, offer to help and share seats in buses. less earphones/headphones too. Beautiful Copenhagen&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-find-a-pizzeria-in-denmark/&quot;&gt;How to Find a Pizzeria in Copenhagen&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 28, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Trip to Laplands, Kiruna]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/a-trip-to-laplands-kiruna/" />
  <id>/blog/a-trip-to-laplands-kiruna</id>
  <published>2016-01-31T23:39:12+01:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-31T23:39:12+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/arrival.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sundsvall&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Sundsvall: changeover&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/xmas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Christmas had arrived&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kiruna1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Rocket in Kiruna town&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kiruna2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;One of the oldest churches in Sweden&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/road.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Road to adventure&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/icehotel1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ice hotel&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Ice hotel: under construction&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/icehotel2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Ice hotel: heaps of snice&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/icebar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;What&#39;s in a glass?&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/aurora.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The Northern lights finally showed up&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kiruna3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Breathtaking landscape&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kiruna4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The architecture can&#39;t escape you&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/back_to_uppsala.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Back to Uppsala&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/a-trip-to-laplands-kiruna/&quot;&gt;A Trip to Laplands, Kiruna&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on January 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Happy Year 2015]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/a-happy-year-2015/" />
  <id>/blog/a-happy-year-2015</id>
  <published>2015-12-31T18:39:59+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-12-31T18:39:59+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The past year has been an amazing journey for me, most of which I have spent in a foreign country. This invariably comes with it’s own
challenges, but the opportunities it has presented have been immense too. My initial trepidation about leaving family, friends and
a not-too-shabby job to pursue
further studies has mostly been displaced by a sense that it has all been worth it. I have had the chance to meet people
from different parts of the world, make new friends, travel quite a bit (I should do more of this) and form networks
that hopefully will outlast my stay in Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so to godsent friends like Dicle, who’ve made my stay interesting and thankfully offered a sneak peek into the bright future…a wholehearted thank you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To baby - &lt;em&gt;kwendete mono&lt;/em&gt;. And to 2016,
more of the same!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/a-happy-year-2015/&quot;&gt;A Happy Year 2015&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on December 31, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Homecoming pt.2]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/homecoming-pt-2/" />
  <id>/blog/homecoming-pt-2</id>
  <published>2015-10-31T22:12:18+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-31T22:12:18+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Looking back on my visit back home last August, I have learnt to appreciate the little things we often take for granted.
Family, friends, experiences, name them. It was especially humbling when my sister invariably asked what food I had missed most so she would prepare it for me. Now, by my recollection, she always cooked chapati on Christmas. Hers are simply the best chapatis I have
ever had the pleasure of eating. And so she made me some: I savored the taste of love in every one of them. This is one of the things that I will
always remember. She gave me the gift of an early Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/chapo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chapati&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Chapo, baked with a sister&#39;s love&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/homecoming-pt-2/&quot;&gt;Homecoming pt.2&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on October 31, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Homecoming pt.1]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/homecoming-pt-1/" />
  <id>/blog/homecoming-pt-1</id>
  <published>2015-09-20T21:42:55+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-20T21:42:55+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;home&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;noun&lt;/em&gt; \ˈhōm\&lt;br /&gt;
:a place of love and comfort that always welcomes you with open arms - and perhaps a plate of freshly baked
cookies - Jaime Meier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past August I had the pleasure of travelling back home after nearly a year away. The summary of my experience away
from home thus far, if you may, would be that nothing really comes close to home. But then again that says nothing about missing the
people I love and care about and life without &lt;em&gt;Ugali&lt;/em&gt; and fish. I digress though: my visit home culminated in the most amazing, nay ethereal 
August a year has ever given me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had occasion to visit my siblings in Rusinga Island where I was met with a lot of interesting new developments. The
first tarmacked road in the entire town had just been completed, transforming the usually topsy-turvy 2 hour journey from Homa Bay
to Mbita into a rather pleasant half an hour ride. Perhaps more indicative of the strides being made in the county,
construction of a bridge spanning the course-way joining the island and Mbita town was underway. Long overdue, some
will dismissively suggest. However, I posit that while a lot more could be done, this is a sign of what we are capable of doing to foster economic progress and deserves applause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/rusinga_bridge1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Rusinga courseway&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/rusinga_bridge2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Men at work&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/rusinga2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Calm waters of L. Victoria&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/rusinga3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Scenic view of Rusinga Island&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/homecoming-pt-1/&quot;&gt;Homecoming pt.1&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on September 20, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oral Exams]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/oral-exams/" />
  <id>/blog/oral-exams</id>
  <published>2015-06-25T05:30:12+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-25T05:30:12+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This past spring was perhaps one of the busiest periods of my studies so far: quite a bit of advanced coursework and projects. Additionally, I
had the novel experience of taking oral examinations for the first time in my student life. 
The oral examinations were typically short (~20 minutes), but very intense in the sense that each question
led onto the next and even the slightest hint of hesitation invited more questions along the same lines. In the
end, I found them quite engaging and interesting - I even had occasion to be asked by one of the teachers what I wanted to be
examined on. Suffice to say that I invariably chose the area I felt I was best prepared for, but the suggestion in itself was incredible to me. But that’s Sweden for you - the teachers and students cooperate to foster learning. The societal structure is flat and the relationship
between teachers (they aren’t even referred to by their doctorate titles) and students is very informal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out that I enjoy oral examinations for the same reasons I enjoy oral interviews: they present an opportunity to
persuade while giving immediate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/oral-exams/&quot;&gt;Oral Exams&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on June 25, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Mothers Day]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/happy-mothers-day/" />
  <id>/blog/happy-mothers-day</id>
  <published>2015-05-14T00:36:20+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-05-14T00:36:20+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1zDFYwx-4mg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/happy-mothers-day/&quot;&gt;Happy Mothers Day&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A tale of two cities]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities/" />
  <id>/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities</id>
  <published>2015-04-30T02:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-30T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer - while this post shares the title with one of my favorite books, that’s where the similarity with Charles
Dickens’ classic ends. The experiences and places depicted here are the author’s own account as seen through often satirical lenses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial plan was to visit Norway over Easter break. However, the Mathematics soon reduced to merely finding a
place with the ‘right’ fare (‘right’ here having a fairly esoteric meaning), and deciding whether it was
worthwhile visiting. And that’s how we settled on the Italian cities Pisa, Rome and Florence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our itinerary took us from Uppsala to Stockholm Skavsta airport, a fairly decent airport without all the
bells and whistles of modern airports - there was neither WiFi nor
Dreamliners for instance. Small metallic containers with the ominous inscriptions “if it fits, it’s free” stood in
several places in the hallway - we were happy to learn that our luggages fit the measurements. That being said, none of the airline staff actually examined the passengers’
luggages to ascertain the bag sizes, which was just as well since I was worried about my bulging backpack
failing to make the mark. About three hours later, we were in Pisa, arriving a few minutes to midnight. It was
immediately apparent that we were no longer in Sweden, our hosts
noticeably gregarious and much less taciturn - loud chatter here, a hearty laugh there and of course the smoke lazily
emanating from a cigarette loosely held in a lady’s delicate hands. Our stay in Pisa was short and sweet: short because
bar the Leaning Tower, there isn’t much else to see. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we visited the Leaning Tower of Pisa at the first opportunity, promptly disappointing my sky-high expectations. My
first encounter with the Tower had been in High school Physics, it’s beauty captivating me as much
as the Laws of Physics it seemingly defied. Years later, I would watch a documentary detailing reconstruction work
undertaken to preserve the tower. Herein lay my gripe: the reconstructions have in my eyes made the tower look newish from the
outside, failing to capture that ancient artistic look I had seen in the Physics text. As I jokingly remarked to my company, the
tower could well have been built last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/leaning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tower&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The Leaning Tower of Pisa&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roma&quot;&gt;Roma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next stop was Roma, a city much warmer than Uppsala and the weather a lot closer to that of Nairobi. How I had
missed this! I could finally walk around in a shirt; the little things we take for granted. We easily located our hostel
from the train station, tucked in a narrow street overlooking
several n-star* hotels. Rome is indeed a touristic city - there is so much to see and so many tourists to see it with
that one would take a lifetime to appreciate
all the attractions. Luckily, we had as our guide a one-time exchange student at our university. 
There are so many cathedrals and squares, and &lt;em&gt;vias&lt;/em&gt; with beautiful
fountains. The Pantheon is a  majestic piece of architecture, housing some of the most
breathtaking artwork I have ever come across - from sculptures to wall art and design. It commands an endless stream of
tourists, merchants and performers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pantheon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pantheon&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Pantheon&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Old Rome was another site I found awe-inspiring, the ruins depicting life in the Roman empire. It seemed almost like
time travel, giving us a sneak peek into ancient Roman civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;old&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Old Rome&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/colosseo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colosseum&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Colosseum&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*n is any number in the range [1, 5].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;florence&quot;&gt;Florence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then embarked on a 3-hour train ride to Florence. The weather here was cooler, a welcome 
escape from the sweltering heat of Rome. While it is often remarked that Florence is a beautiful city, my impression was
that the same could be said of Rome. The city is far quieter, has less tourists and generally comes off as a perfect
place to relax. We visited the Florence Cathedral, located in Piazza del Duomo and includes a Baptistry and
Giotto’s Campanile. We also visited several art galleries featuring marvelous paintings and sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/florence.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Florence Cathedral&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/hercules.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hercules&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Hercules fighting the Centaur Nessus&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our stay in Florence drew to a close, I decidedly wanted to experience the famed “Italian cuisine” one more time. So
I located a restaurant close to our hostel (the best hostel out of the three we stayed in). I ordered pizza recommended
by the affable Cuban waitress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where are you from?” she ventured into small talk as I waited for my order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Kenya.” I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, Africa. I am from Cuba. Fidel…” I nodded, affirming that I knew Cuba and Fidel’s second name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in the restaurant with gentle showers falling, my thoughts wandered. For the first time during the trip, I was
able to afford the luxury of sitting still. We had wanted to make the most of our stay in Italy: visit monuments,
cathedrals, art galleries, squares, bridges…all the things normal tourists do. Rarely had we taken time to savor the moments. I wondered whether we were victims of what Daniel Kahneman
calls the “experiencing self” and the “remembering self” in his fantastic book &lt;em&gt;Thinking - Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;; too eager to whip out our cameras and shoot away rather than marvel at the enchanting beauty in whose presence we were lucky to stand. And that’s how I decided to shake off my company and
drift a bit on my own. I wanted to just sit down and take it all in for a while - I had seen enough of the tourist
stuff anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Three minutes.” the waitress announced, indicating with her fingers the time left before my pizza was ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pizza arrived, I wolfed it down, adding a generous portion of olive oil. Good, but not great. An upgrade on
Rififi pizzeria in Uppsala though. Our flight back was due in a few hours 
and my companion was probably worried about my whereabouts. I handed the waitress a 10 Euro note and briskly walked
towards
the hostel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Grazie mille” she said as I made my way though the street.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities/&quot;&gt;A tale of two cities&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Välkommen spring]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/Welcome-Spring/" />
  <id>/blog/Welcome-Spring</id>
  <published>2015-04-16T06:00:55+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-16T06:00:55+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Winter is gone, spring is finally here! The weather is good, the sun 
lifting the gloom off most people’s faces. Seeing snow for the fist time
was definitely exciting, but spring weather is way more benign. Here are 
some pictures I’ve taken over the course of last autumn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uppsala cathedral&lt;/em&gt;: tall, imposing buiding with great architecture. Visible from most parts of
the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/cathedral.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Uppsala domkyrka&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;em&gt;Flustret&lt;/em&gt;: one of the first places our guide took us to. As he pointed out, flustret 
literally translates to “mouth of the beehive”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/flustret.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Flustret&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/flustret2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret2&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Another view of Flustret&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
3. &lt;em&gt;Wild ducks&lt;/em&gt;: one never fails to notice the ducks in the pond next to Flustret. They disappear during winter and reappear around spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/ducks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ducks&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Ducks&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. &lt;em&gt;Fyris river&lt;/em&gt; flows right through the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/fyris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;river fyris&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Fyris river&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
5. &lt;strong&gt;Välkommen till Eklundshof&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Swedish isn’t very hard to pick up, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/eklushofsvagen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;eklunds&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The  way home&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/eklunds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;eklunds2&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;My adopted home&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/Welcome-Spring/&quot;&gt;Välkommen spring&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[♯147notjustanumber]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/%23147notjustanumber/" />
  <id>/blog/#147notjustanumber</id>
  <published>2015-04-09T06:00:55+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-09T06:00:55+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/147.png-large&quot; alt=&quot;147&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;We Shall Not Forget&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past week on 2nd April, 147 students at Garissa University
had their lives and dreams cut short by terrorists’ guns. These students represented 
the hopes and aspirations of
their families (and sometimes whole communities). For the innocent victims of this
most inhuman attack, their lives is the heavy price our nation had to pay in failing to provide  adequate
security to its citizens. They were our sisters, brothers, sons, daughters, cousins, uncles, relatives and friends. 
They’re not just 147 people: they’ve got names and we honour their memory &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23147notjustanumber&amp;amp;src=tyah&quot; targe=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#147notjustanumber&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/%23147notjustanumber/&quot;&gt;♯147notjustanumber&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 09, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy cake day!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/happy-birthday-baby/" />
  <id>/blog/happy-birthday-baby</id>
  <published>2015-04-02T06:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-02T06:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This is the first post on this website and time has so willed that today is my baby’s birthday. I wanted to take a moment to say how much of a blessing you have been to me. Looking back, not even in my wildest imaginations would I have exptected a chance meeting in a petrol station to turn out quite like it has. See, I had to turn back and follow you after you had passed me, while pretending to be headed in the same direction as you were. Thankfully, the noise coming from the nearby garage ensured that my increased heartbeats did not expose my nervousness…or at least that’s what I assumed. In the end, it was well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for all the moments we have shared - I’ve learnt a lot from you and I can unequivocally say that I’ve become a better man since you came into my life. You are an amazing person, and while circumstances forbid us from celebrating the birthday together, I’d like to wish you many happy days ahead; full of smiles and laughter. And Sunday love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Birthday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sheri.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sheri&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/happy-birthday-baby/&quot;&gt;Happy cake day!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>