<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text"></title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2015-06-25T06:40:35+02:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Got</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oral Exams]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/oral-exams/" />
  <id>/blog/oral-exams</id>
  <published>2015-06-25T05:30:12+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-25T05:30:12+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This past spring was perhaps one of the busiest periods of my studies so far: quite a bit of advanced coursework and projects. Additionally, I
had the novel experience of taking oral examinations for the first time in my student life. 
The oral examinations were typically short (~20 minutes), but very intense in the sense that each question
led onto the next and even the slightest hint of hesitation invited more questions along the same lines. In the
end, I found them quite engaging and interesting - I even had occasion to be asked by one of the teachers what I wanted to be
examined on. Suffice to say that I invariably chose the area I felt I was best prepared for, but the suggestion in itself was incredible to me. But that’s Sweden for you - the teachers and students cooperate to foster learning. The societal structure is flat and the relationship
between teachers (they aren’t even referred to by their doctorate titles) and students is very informal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out that I enjoy oral examinations for the same reasons I enjoy oral interviews: they present an opportunity to
persuade while giving immediate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/oral-exams/&quot;&gt;Oral Exams&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on June 25, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Mothers Day]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/happy-mothers-day/" />
  <id>/blog/happy-mothers-day</id>
  <published>2015-05-14T00:36:20+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-05-14T00:36:20+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1zDFYwx-4mg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/happy-mothers-day/&quot;&gt;Happy Mothers Day&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 14, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A tale of two cities]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities/" />
  <id>/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities</id>
  <published>2015-04-30T02:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-30T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer - while this post shares the title with one of my favorite books, that’s where the similarity with Charles
Dickens’ classic ends. The experiences and places depicted here are the author’s own account as seen through often satirical lenses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial plan was to visit Norway over Easter break. However, the Mathematics soon reduced to merely finding a
place with the ‘right’ fare (‘right’ here having a fairly esoteric meaning), and deciding whether it was
worthwhile visiting. And that’s how we settled on the Italian cities Pisa, Rome and Florence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our itinerary took us from Uppsala to Stockholm Skavsta airport, a fairly decent airport without all the
bells and whistles of modern airports - there was neither WiFi nor
Dreamliners for instance. Small metallic containers with the ominous inscriptions “if it fits, it’s free” stood in
several places in the hallway - we were happy to learn that our luggages fit the measurements. That being said, none of the airline staff actually examined the passengers’
luggages to ascertain the bag sizes, which was just as well since I was worried about my bulging backpack
failing to make the mark. About three hours later, we were in Pisa, arriving a few minutes to midnight. It was
immediately apparent that we were no longer in Sweden, our hosts
noticeably gregarious and much less taciturn - loud chatter here, a hearty laugh there and of course the smoke lazily
emanating from a cigarette loosely held in a lady’s delicate hands. Our stay in Pisa was short and sweet: short because
bar the Leaning Tower, there isn’t much else to see. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we visited the Leaning Tower of Pisa at the first opportunity, promptly disappointing my sky-high expectations. My
first encounter with the Tower had been in High school Physics, it’s beauty captivating me as much
as the Laws of Physics it seemingly defied. Years later, I would watch a documentary detailing reconstruction work
undertaken to preserve the tower. Herein lay my gripe: the reconstructions have in my eyes made the tower look newish from the
outside, failing to capture that ancient artistic look I had seen in the Physics text. As I jokingly remarked to my company, the
tower could well have been built last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/leaning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tower&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The Leaning Tower of Pisa&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roma&quot;&gt;Roma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next stop was Roma, a city much warmer than Uppsala and the weather a lot closer to that of Nairobi. How I had
missed this! I could finally walk around in a shirt; the little things we take for granted. We easily located our hostel
from the train station, tucked in a narrow street overlooking
several n-star* hotels. Rome is indeed a touristic city - there is so much to see and so many tourists to see it with
that one would take a lifetime to appreciate
all the attractions. Luckily, we had as our guide a one-time exchange student at our university. 
There are so many cathedrals and squares, and &lt;em&gt;vias&lt;/em&gt; with beautiful
fountains. The Pantheon is a  majestic piece of architecture, housing some of the most
breathtaking artwork I have ever come across - from sculptures to wall art and design. It commands an endless stream of
tourists, merchants and performers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/pantheon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pantheon&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Pantheon&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Old Rome was another site I found awe-inspiring, the ruins depicting life in the Roman empire. It seemed almost like
time travel, giving us a sneak peek into ancient Roman civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/old.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;old&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Old Rome&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/colosseo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Colosseum&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Colosseum&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*n is any number in the range [1, 5].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;florence&quot;&gt;Florence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then embarked on a 3-hour train ride to Florence. The weather here was cooler, a welcome 
escape from the sweltering heat of Rome. While it is often remarked that Florence is a beautiful city, my impression was
that the same could be said of Rome. The city is far quieter, has less tourists and generally comes off as a perfect
place to relax. We visited the Florence Cathedral, located in Piazza del Duomo and includes a Baptistry and
Giotto’s Campanile. We also visited several art galleries featuring marvelous paintings and sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/florence.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Florence Cathedral&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/hercules.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hercules&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Hercules fighting the Centaur Nessus&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our stay in Florence drew to a close, I decidedly wanted to experience the famed “Italian cuisine” one more time. So
I located a restaurant close to our hostel (the best hostel out of the three we stayed in). I ordered pizza recommended
by the affable Cuban waitress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where are you from?” she ventured into small talk as I waited for my order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Kenya.” I replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, Africa. I am from Cuba. Fidel…” I nodded, affirming that I knew Cuba and Fidel’s second name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in the restaurant with gentle showers falling, my thoughts wandered. For the first time during the trip, I was
able to afford the luxury of sitting still. We had wanted to make the most of our stay in Italy: visit monuments,
cathedrals, art galleries, squares, bridges…all the things normal tourists do. Rarely had we taken time to savor the moments. I wondered whether we were victims of what Daniel Kahneman
calls the “experiencing self” and the “remembering self” in his fantastic book &lt;em&gt;Thinking - Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;; too eager to whip out our cameras and shoot away rather than marvel at the enchanting beauty in whose presence we were lucky to stand. And that’s how I decided to shake off my company and
drift a bit on my own. I wanted to just sit down and take it all in for a while - I had seen enough of the tourist
stuff anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Three minutes.” the waitress announced, indicating with her fingers the time left before my pizza was ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pizza arrived, I wolfed it down, adding a generous portion of olive oil. Good, but not great. An upgrade on
Rififi pizzeria in Uppsala though. Our flight back was due in a few hours 
and my companion was probably worried about my whereabouts. I handed the waitress a 10 Euro note and briskly walked
towards
the hostel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Grazie mille” she said as I made my way though the street.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/A-Tale-Of-Two-Cities/&quot;&gt;A tale of two cities&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Välkommen spring]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/Welcome-Spring/" />
  <id>/blog/Welcome-Spring</id>
  <published>2015-04-16T06:00:55+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-16T06:00:55+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Winter is gone, spring is finally here! The weather is good, the sun 
lifting the gloom off most people’s faces. Seeing snow for the fist time
was definitely exciting, but spring weather is way more benign. Here are 
some pictures I’ve taken over the course of last autumn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uppsala cathedral&lt;/em&gt;: tall, imposing buiding with great architecture. Visible from most parts of
the city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/cathedral.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cathedral&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Uppsala domkyrka&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
2. &lt;em&gt;Flustret&lt;/em&gt;: one of the first places our guide took us to. As he pointed out, flustret 
literally translates to “mouth of the beehive”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/flustret.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Flustret&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/flustret2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flustret2&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Another view of Flustret&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
3. &lt;em&gt;Wild ducks&lt;/em&gt;: one never fails to notice the ducks in the pond next to Flustret. They disappear during winter and reappear around spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/ducks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ducks&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Ducks&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
4. &lt;em&gt;Fyris river&lt;/em&gt; flows right through the city centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/fyris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;river fyris&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Fyris river&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
5. &lt;strong&gt;Välkommen till Eklundshof&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Swedish isn’t very hard to pick up, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/eklushofsvagen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;eklunds&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;The  way home&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/eklunds.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;eklunds2&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;My adopted home&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/Welcome-Spring/&quot;&gt;Välkommen spring&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 16, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[♯147notjustanumber]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/blog/%23147notjustanumber/" />
  <id>/blog/#147notjustanumber</id>
  <published>2015-04-09T06:00:55+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-09T06:00:55+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Got</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>kcingot@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;!--includes/image.html--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrapper&quot;&gt; 
     
        &lt;img src=&quot;/images/147.png-large&quot; alt=&quot;147&quot; /&gt; 
         
     
    &lt;p class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;We Shall Not Forget&lt;/p&gt; 
     
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past week on 2nd April, 147 students at Garissa University
had their lives and dreams cut short by terrorists’ guns. These students represented 
the hopes and aspirations of
their families (and sometimes whole communities). For the innocent victims of this
most inhuman attack, their lives is the heavy price our nation had to pay in failing to provide  adequate
security to its citizens. They were our sisters, brothers, sons, daughters, cousins, uncles, relatives and friends. 
They’re not just 147 people: they’ve got names and we honour their memory &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23147notjustanumber&amp;amp;src=tyah&quot; targe=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;#147notjustanumber&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/%23147notjustanumber/&quot;&gt;♯147notjustanumber&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Got at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 09, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>